We ask a lot of questions
about our diet.
What’s the right way to
treat a chronic illness?
Fight off a virus,
lose weight?
The problem is, we get
a lot of different answers.
Well, I’m here to help.
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Today, in part three of
our series on Ozempic,
we look at how to control the
side effects of GLP-1 drugs.
It appears the vast majority
of people prescribed GLP-1 drugs
stop taking them
in a matter of months.
But compare that
to older weight loss drugs.
Those had a 98 percent
failure rate.
As I’ve mentioned,
in drug trials,
most people taking
these types of weight-loss drugs
started out obese
and ended up obese
no matter how long
they stayed on them,
but that’s just on average.
Some people, despite being
on high-dose Ozempic for years,
actually ended up heavier
than when they started,
and most remained overweight,
but a small fraction of them,
about 1 in 25,
plateaued down
at a normal weight.
One in 25
doesn’t sound like a lot,
but obese individuals
are rarely able
to achieve a normal weight.
Without something drastic,
like bariatric surgery,
only about 1 in 200 men
with class 1 obesity,
or 1 in 100 women,
are able to find their way back
to a normal weight;
so, these drugs
really can have a huge effect
on a select few.
Of course, you’d presumably
have to stay on them forever
to maintain that weight loss
at a cost of maybe $16,000
a year.
But even for those
who can afford the cost,
the main reason
they stop taking GLP-1 drugs
is the gastrointestinal
side-effect profile.
The most common side effects
of Ozempic-type drugs
include nausea, vomiting,
diarrhea, and constipation.
And they may also heighten
the risk of pancreatitis,
kidney failure,
and thyroid cancer,
but for now, let’s stick
to the common ones.
These significant adverse
gastrointestinal effects
were demonstrated
in virtually all trials,
though they weren’t bad enough
to cause more than 15 percent
of trial participants
to drop out,
and the vast majority
of adverse effects got better
after they stopped the drugs.
Here are the numbers:
44 percent
experienced nausea,
30 percent diarrhea,
24 percent vomiting,
24 percent constipation,
and 20 percent
abdominal pain.
But 16 percent of those
on the placebo injections
experienced nausea
or diarrhea too;
so, it wasn’t all due
to the drug.
People don’t tend to just
spontaneously vomit, though;
so, that’s more likely
to be a drug-induced effect.
So, some people may not
experience side effects at all,
and these GI side effects
have been shown
likely to be dose-dependent,
and more common during
the dose escalation period.
Thus, it’s recommended
that these medications
are started at lower doses
and only increased
as tolerated.
So, starting low
and going slow,
gradually nudging up the dose
over many months,
can minimize
some of these side effects.
And in terms
of what patients can do:
Eat slowly,
smaller portions.
Eat a low-fat diet.
Small sips of fluid.
Get some fresh air.
Crackers, apples, mint, ginger.
Stay hydrated.
Avoid sports drinks,
dairy products,
coffee, alcohol,
and soft drinks.
Temporarily reduce your intake
of fiber or increase it,
depending on symptoms.
And if things get really bad,
avoid drinking during meals.
If the symptoms persist
or worsen,
let your healthcare provider
know ASAP.
One thing your doctor can do
is prescribe anti-vomiting drugs
to counter the side effects
of the original drugs,
but if you don’t feel nauseated
all the time,
will you still lose weight?
Yes, even people who don’t
feel sick to their stomach
can experience
the appetite suppression
that leads to weight loss.
GLP-1 also makes you
feel fuller for longer
by slowing down the rate at
which food leaves your stomach.
That contributes
to the nausea and vomiting,
and can lead
to a serious complication
if you have to go under
anesthesia for surgery.
GLP-1 drugs slow
your stomach down so much
that the American Society
of Anesthesiologists
recommends people
stop taking the drugs
for up to a week prior
to procedures
so you don’t go under the knife
with a full stomach,
for fear that you’ll aspirate
stomach contents
into your lungs.
It turns out that may not
even be long enough.
Patients taking these drugs
had a higher prevalence
of increased residual
gastric contents despite fasting
even if they stopped
these drugs a week before.
So, if you’re going in
for elective surgery,
consider stopping a drug
like Ozempic
at least three weeks before.
Stopping these drugs
for a month or so
may not be tenable
for diabetics
using it to control
their blood sugars,
but if you’re just doing it
for your weight,
it’s a good idea to hold off.
GLP-1 type drugs, like Ozempic,
function by making patients
feel fuller, eat less,
and hence, lose weight.
However, an important
but often overlooked factor
in these studies
of these kinds of drugs
relates to the type of weight
that’s lost.
Typically, when people
who are obese lose weight,
the decrease
in their fat-free mass,
meaning essentially
their lean mass,
including their muscles,
usually represents
about 25 percent
of their total weight loss.
So, for every 4 pounds (2 kg)
lost on the scale,
one of those pounds is not fat.
But on drugs like Ozempic,
as much as 40 percent
of the total weight lost
is that lean mass, nearly half
the pounds you’re losing.
Those on Ozempic
or tirzepatide,
a newer GLP-1 drug
sold as Zepbound,
lost about 14 pounds (6 kg)
of lean mass,
about one eighth of all
the lean mass in their body.
That’s worse than the amount
of lean mass you lose
when you have
esophageal cancer,
or head and neck cancer.
Now, some people paid
by the pharma companies
that make GLP-1-type drugs
question whether the amount
of muscle mass loss
is clinically relevant.
But these drugs cause
such rapid and significant loss
of lean mass,
that it’s comparable
to how much you’d lose
over a decade or more of aging.
The drug industry consultants
argue that even if 40 percent
of the weight lost
is lean mass,
that still means the majority,
60 percent, is fat;
so, you end up
with a better fat-to-lean ratio,
in the end.
But that’s just
on the first go-around.
Remember, most people
don’t stick to these drugs
for more than a few months,
either because
they can’t keep paying
a thousand bucks a month
for them,
or they don’t want to put up
with all the side effects,
or deal with drug shortages,
or run out of refills.
And when you stop these drugs,
we know the lost body fat
piles on back,
but there’s a concern
that any lost muscle mass
may not;
so, you then actually end up
fatter in the end.
This kind of weight cycling
has been associated
with extra fat deposition
on the body,
especially around the middle.
Using the gold-standard method,
MRI,
to directly visualize
muscle mass,
researchers found
that the more times
people cycle their weight,
the worse their body composition
appears to get.
The profound level
of lean mass loss
associated
with GLP-1 weight-loss drugs
would be expected
to have deleterious impacts
on health outcomes,
including increased frailty
and perhaps greater
long-term mortality risk,
though, this concern
remains theoretical,
since any such long-term data
have yet to be published.
The good news is there’s
something we can do about it.
Exercise, particularly
resistance exercise,
like weight training,
can cut in half or more
the proportion
of fat-free mass that is lost.
Check this out:
Based on half a dozen studies
of caloric restriction
for weight loss
(like portion control),
and the same calorie restriction
plus resistance exercise,
the non-exercising group
lost more weight.
You can guess why, though,
because without
the resistance exercise,
they lost more lean mass,
whereas the exercising group
lost nine pounds (4 kg)
apparently without losing
any lean mass.
Supervised resistance training
interventions,
up to a few times a week
for more than 10 weeks,
where all major muscle groups
are worked,
can add a few extra pounds
of lean mass.
More with weights than cardio,
more when younger,
and more in men than women.
Collectively, this evidence
supports resistance training
as an effective approach
to, at the very least,
help mitigate
the decrease in lean mass;
so, programs such as these
should be adopted without delay
in patients embarking
on Ozempic-type therapy.
What about "Ozempic face"?
The term has consumed the media
with the medication’s
rising popularity
and describes rapid weight loss
in the face
that leaves
a distorted appearance.
And I’d never even heard
of Ozempic butt.
Media reports have linked
the drug to facial aging,
but perhaps it’s not so much
the medication
as much as the potent
weight-loss effects
that leave a sagging appearance
due to the loss of fat
in the face.
While this seems logical,
the explanation cannot
fully account
for the markedly accelerated
facial aging
seen in GLP-1 drug patients.
The premature facial aging
and altered skin health
appears to be multifactorial,
involving not only the loss
of fat in the face,
but an effect on stem cells
and the production
and secretion of hormonal
and metabolic factors.
These changes compromise
the structural integrity
and barrier function
of the skin
and may lead to diminished
facial muscle mass as well,
further exacerbating
the appearance of aging.
Another side effect of rapid
weight loss is gallstones,
which is not limited
to GLP-1 drugs.
Shedding
all that excess cholesterol
stored in your fat cells
can lead to it crystallizing
in your bile like rock candy,
forming gallstones.
Something else to be
cognizant of,
but in a way,
both the muscle loss
and gallstones
may just be signs
of how effective
these drugs can be
for losing weight.
But as semaglutide’s
popularity soars,
rare but serious adverse effects
are emerging.
Like, what about possible
thyroid cancer, pancreatitis,
kidney problems, depression,
or suicidal thoughts?
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
If you hear about any graphs, charts,
graphics, images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
My latest major book,
“How Not to Age” is out.
Check it out from your
local public library.
I also wrote a
mini book on Ozempic.
Available in softcover,
e-book, and audio versions.
Check it out on NutritionFacts.org.
And of course, all the proceeds
I receive of the sales
of all my books goes
directly to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the
website is free.
There are no ads,
no corporate sponsorships,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.